<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Grit-2500 on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/tags/grit-2500/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 23:56:25 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/tags/grit-2500/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Remove 1500–2000 Grit Marks On Resin</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/remove-1500-2000-grit-marks-on-resin-resin-polishing/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/remove-1500-2000-grit-marks-on-resin-resin-polishing/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 23:56:25 +0000</pubDate><category>Resin Polishing</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1200</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-2500</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>dust control</category><description>Expert workflows to remove 1500–2000 grit marks on resin and achieve optical clarity with the right abrasives, compounds, and heat control.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="resin-polishing-erasing-15002000-grit-scratches"&gt;Resin Polishing: Erasing 1500–2000 Grit Scratches&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pendant looked flawless on the bench last night—glassy, color suspended in amber, edges softened just so. Then morning light hit it. Under a low-angle window beam, micro-scratches flared across the surface like frost on a windshield. You could feel your shoulders sag. You did the careful wet-sand through 1500 and 2000, kept the strokes even, swirled the slurry away. It should be done. But resin is unforgiving under raking light, and 1500–2000 grit marks hang on, whisper-thin but brutally visible. This is the moment where the craft turns from “sanding” to resin polishing: closing the cut, controlling heat, and stepping the abrasive system with intent until the surface stops being a surface and becomes a reflection.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>9</readingTime></item><item><title>Soap To Water Ratio For Lubrication</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/soap-to-water-ratio-for-lubrication-wet-dry-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/soap-to-water-ratio-for-lubrication-wet-dry-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 14:24:10 +0000</pubDate><category>Waterproof &amp; Wet/Dry Paper</category><category>grit-360</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-1200</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-2500</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>sanding block</category><description>Engineer-tested soap-to-water ratios for lubricating wet dry sandpaper on paint, wood, and metal. Get precise mixes, tips, and troubleshooting.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="optimal-soap-to-water-ratio-for-wet-dry-sandpaper"&gt;Optimal Soap to Water Ratio for Wet Dry Sandpaper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, a quiet garage, and a project you’ve promised yourself you’d finally finish. The headlight lenses are foggy. The table top has those telltale dust nibs in the polyurethane. A chef’s knife hangs dull on the magnetic strip, begging for bite. You fill a bucket, reach for a bottle of soap, and lay out sheets of wet dry sandpaper—ready to get to work. And then you pause. How much soap should actually go into the water? One drop? A teaspoon? More? You’ve heard “soapy water helps it glide,” but glide isn’t the only variable that matters. There’s also bite, swarf transport, scratch control, and heat. The soap-to-water ratio dictates whether you refine fast and clean—or skate on a film that kills cutting speed and blurs feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>Best Wet Sanding Sequence For Plastic Headlight Lenses</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/best-wet-sanding-sequence-for-plastic-headlight-lenses-lens-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/best-wet-sanding-sequence-for-plastic-headlight-lenses-lens-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 03:51:43 +0000</pubDate><category>Headlight Restoration</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-800</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1200</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-2500</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>dry sanding</category><description>A precise, technical guide to wet lens sanding for plastic headlights—abrasives, workflows, and UV protection to restore clear, durable optics.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="best-lens-sanding-sequence-for-plastic-headlights"&gt;Best Lens Sanding Sequence for Plastic Headlights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twilight is the worst time to discover your headlights are lying to you. Streetlights smear into blurry halos; lane markers fade into a matte wash. You feel yourself leaning forward in the seat as if posture could coax more lumens from the housings. But the problem isn’t the bulb; it’s the lens. Polycarbonate oxidizes, turns porous, and grows a diffuse surface that scatters light instead of transmitting it. That’s fixable if you stop thinking of restoration as a wipe-on miracle and start treating it like precision surface engineering. This guide is about real lens sanding—structured, wet, and sequential—not guessing with a single pad until it “looks better.”&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>Crosshatch Sanding Pattern For Even Clear Coat Leveling</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/crosshatch-sanding-pattern-for-even-clear-coat-leveling-clear-coat-leveling/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/crosshatch-sanding-pattern-for-even-clear-coat-leveling-clear-coat-leveling/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:59:26 +0000</pubDate><category>Wet Sanding Clear Coat</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-2500</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>clear coat</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>sanding block</category><description>Learn the crosshatch sanding pattern for even clear coat leveling—tools, grits, steps, and pro tips for a flat, glossy, mirror-like finish.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="crosshatch-sanding-for-clear-coat-leveling"&gt;Crosshatch Sanding for Clear Coat Leveling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You notice it first when the sun dips behind a cloud. Your car—or maybe that guitar body you’ve been refinishing—looked perfect in full daylight. But now a soft, diffused glow reveals a faint orange peel, a sprinkling of swirls, and the slightest rippling along a contour line. It’s not ruined, but it’s not the glassy surface you had in mind. The promise of a flawless finish is what pulls many of us into the workshop on a Saturday morning, and it’s what makes techniques like clear coat leveling feel less like a chore and more like craftsmanship. What you need isn’t more product or a heavier hand; it’s a repeatable way to flatten texture without taking unnecessary risks.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Use Diamond Or Sic For Glass Edges</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/use-diamond-or-sic-for-glass-edges-glass-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/use-diamond-or-sic-for-glass-edges-glass-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 23:29:24 +0000</pubDate><category>Glass &amp; Ceramics Sanding</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-240</category><category>grit-280</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-800</category><category>grit-1200</category><category>grit-2500</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>wet sanding</category><description>Technical guide to glass sanding for chip‑free edges using diamond or SiC abrasives, with grit sequences, coolant control, and polishing workflows.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="glass-sanding-for-clean-safe-edges-diamond-vs-sic"&gt;Glass sanding for clean, safe edges: diamond vs SiC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment you lift a freshly cut pane, you feel it: the edge that looks fine from arm’s length but carries invisible threats—micro-chips, stress risers, and the slight granular drag under a fingertip that says the finish is not ready for handling. Anyone who has ever fit a glass shelf, framed a museum-grade print, or repurposed a bottle knows that the edge is where projects succeed or fail. That’s where glass sanding earns its keep. Thoughtful abrasive selection and disciplined technique turn a risky raw cut into a safe, optically clean edge that won’t shed fragments, haze, or propagate cracks under load. Whether you’re tuning a small arris for furniture-grade touch or chasing an optical polish on a laminated panel, the goal is the same: remove damage quickly, control heat, and leave a tight subsurface that won’t surprise you months later.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>14</readingTime></item></channel></rss>