<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Wet Sanding Clear Coat on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/categories/wet-sanding-clear-coat/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/categories/wet-sanding-clear-coat/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Compound Versus Polish Differences For Clear Coat Finishing</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/11/compound-versus-polish-differences-for-clear-coat-finishing-paint-polishing/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/11/compound-versus-polish-differences-for-clear-coat-finishing-paint-polishing/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 05:56:37 +0000</pubDate><category>Wet Sanding Clear Coat</category><category>grit-800</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-2500</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>clear coat</category><category>wet sanding</category><description>Understand compound vs polish for clear coat finishing with sanding workflows, abrasive selection, and process control for defect-free paint polishing.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="paint-polishing-compound-vs-polish-for-clear-coat"&gt;Paint polishing: compound vs polish for clear coat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Saturday morning sun can be the most unforgiving inspector you’ll ever meet. You back the car out after a late-night respray—coffee in hand, optimism high—and the light slices across the hood like a straightedge. Orange peel you knew about, sure. But then the swirls appear, whisper-fine arcs barely visible at dusk now glaring at full volume. You feel them before you see them: the drag of a microfiber catching on texture, the way your eyes follow a ghosty hologram around a curved fender. This is the moment when “wash and wax” ends and craft begins—where surface preparation, abrasive control, and paint polishing decide whether you get a mirror or a mirage.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/17.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>Crosshatch Sanding Pattern For Even Clear Coat Leveling</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/crosshatch-sanding-pattern-for-even-clear-coat-leveling-clear-coat-leveling/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/crosshatch-sanding-pattern-for-even-clear-coat-leveling-clear-coat-leveling/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:59:26 +0000</pubDate><category>Wet Sanding Clear Coat</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-2500</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>clear coat</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>sanding block</category><description>Learn the crosshatch sanding pattern for even clear coat leveling—tools, grits, steps, and pro tips for a flat, glossy, mirror-like finish.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="crosshatch-sanding-for-clear-coat-leveling"&gt;Crosshatch Sanding for Clear Coat Leveling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You notice it first when the sun dips behind a cloud. Your car—or maybe that guitar body you’ve been refinishing—looked perfect in full daylight. But now a soft, diffused glow reveals a faint orange peel, a sprinkling of swirls, and the slightest rippling along a contour line. It’s not ruined, but it’s not the glassy surface you had in mind. The promise of a flawless finish is what pulls many of us into the workshop on a Saturday morning, and it’s what makes techniques like clear coat leveling feel less like a chore and more like craftsmanship. What you need isn’t more product or a heavier hand; it’s a repeatable way to flatten texture without taking unnecessary risks.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>How To Wet Sand Clear Coat Without Burning Through Edges</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/02/how-to-wet-sand-clear-coat-without-burning-through-edges-wet-sanding-clear-coat/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/02/how-to-wet-sand-clear-coat-without-burning-through-edges-wet-sanding-clear-coat/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 23:14:03 +0000</pubDate><category>Wet Sanding Clear Coat</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><category>sanding block</category><category>grit progression</category><description>Learn the art of wet sanding clear coat to achieve a flawless finish without burning through edges. Expert tips and step-by-step guidance included.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="mastering-wet-sanding-clear-coat-without-burn-through"&gt;Mastering Wet Sanding Clear Coat Without Burn-Through&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stepping into your garage, the scent of fresh paint still lingers in the air, mingling with the familiar aroma of motor oil and sawdust. Your latest project—a classic car restoration—is nearing completion. The bodywork shines under the fluorescent lights, but there’s one more crucial step to perfect that gleaming finish: wet sanding the clear coat. You’ve heard horror stories of burn-throughs, where a moment of inattention turns a pristine surface into a repair nightmare. But today, armed with the right knowledge, you&amp;rsquo;ll transform that intimidating task into a rewarding craft.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>6</readingTime></item></channel></rss>