<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Ceramic &amp; Premium Abrasives on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/categories/ceramic--premium-abrasives/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 13:30:02 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/categories/ceramic--premium-abrasives/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Reduced Heat And Loading On Tough Materials</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/16/reduced-heat-and-loading-on-tough-materials-ceramic-sanding-discs/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/16/reduced-heat-and-loading-on-tough-materials-ceramic-sanding-discs/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 13:30:01 +0000</pubDate><category>Ceramic &amp; Premium Abrasives</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-180</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>dry sanding</category><description>Engineer-tested review of ceramic sanding discs—how they cut cooler, resist loading, and last longer on stainless, hardwoods, and composites.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="ceramic-sanding-discs-for-cooler-cleaner-cuts"&gt;Ceramic Sanding Discs for Cooler, Cleaner Cuts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late on a Saturday, the garage hums like a small factory. The goal is modest—deburr a few stainless brackets, flatten a maple cutting board, and knock down drips on a fiberglass canoe repair—but the reality is a stack of spent discs, a hot sander, and surfaces that look worse with every pass. You can smell scorched wood and feel the sander dragging as the face clogs with resin and dust. The disc you just installed is already glazed. It’s the kind of session that makes you wonder if sanding is a test of patience rather than a controllable, measurable process.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/22.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Longer Life Versus Standard Abrasives</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/longer-life-versus-standard-abrasives-ceramic-sanding-discs/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/longer-life-versus-standard-abrasives-ceramic-sanding-discs/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 13:31:19 +0000</pubDate><category>Ceramic &amp; Premium Abrasives</category><category>grit-60</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-360</category><category>dust control</category><category>grit progression</category><description>Compare ceramic sanding discs to standard abrasives, with actionable setup tips, workflows, and cost math to extend life and elevate surface quality.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="ceramic-sanding-discs-vs-standard-longer-life"&gt;Ceramic sanding discs vs standard: longer life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dust collector hummed like a steady metronome as Marcus leaned into the oak tabletop, fighting a familiar battle against swirl marks and rising heat. He’d already burned through three conventional discs by mid-afternoon, each one cutting hard for a minute and then fading into a smear of loading and noise. With dinner guests arriving at seven and the table still scarred from yesterday’s router tear-out, frustration felt inevitable. His phone chimed: a colleague’s message, short and to the point—“Try ceramic sanding discs. Run lighter pressure. Keep it moving.” He shrugged, swapped the pad, and clipped on a mesh-backed ceramic disc he’d picked up on a whim.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>When Ceramic Outperforms Aluminum Oxide</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/when-ceramic-outperforms-aluminum-oxide-ceramic-sanding-discs/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/when-ceramic-outperforms-aluminum-oxide-ceramic-sanding-discs/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 13:34:14 +0000</pubDate><category>Ceramic &amp; Premium Abrasives</category><category>grit-60</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-180</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><category>dust control</category><description>Learn when ceramic sanding discs beat aluminum oxide: cut rate, heat control, cost per part, and pro tips for metal, wood, and composites.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="when-ceramic-sanding-discs-outperform-aluminum-oxide"&gt;When Ceramic Sanding Discs Outperform Aluminum Oxide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a quiet Saturday morning, the garage becomes your studio. You’ve cleared a workbench, lined up clamps and rags, and lit the space with a warm shop lamp. The project is personal: a welded steel coffee table for the living room, something sturdy and simple that can hold the weight of everyday life. The first passes with a grinder feel hopeful—until the discs start glazing. Heat builds, paint smears, and the cut slows to a crawl. You switch to a finer grit, then back again, but the aluminum oxide discs keep dulling, forcing you to lean harder. The surface looks scuffed but not flat, and your shoulders ache from forcing the tool to do what the abrasive simply won’t.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item></channel></rss>