<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Paint Prep on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/tags/paint-prep/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 13:37:10 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/tags/paint-prep/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Strip Failing Polyurethane Then Sand Residue Before Refinishing</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/12/strip-failing-polyurethane-then-sand-residue-before-refinishing-coating-removal/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/12/strip-failing-polyurethane-then-sand-residue-before-refinishing-coating-removal/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 13:37:09 +0000</pubDate><category>Paint Removal &amp; Surface Prep</category><category>paint prep</category><category>rust removal</category><category>primer coat</category><category>sanding block</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-1500</category><description>Learn expert steps for coating removal, sanding residue, and refinishing wood for durable, beautiful results with safe methods, tools, and pro tips.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="coating-removal-and-refinishing-failing-polyurethane"&gt;Coating Removal and Refinishing Failing Polyurethane&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning light spilled across the dining table you’ve hosted around for years. You set down a mug and notice the surface clings just a little; a ring remains, faint but stubborn. Along the edges, the once-smooth finish has turned brittle and chalky, tiny flakes catching the light like dust motes in motion. You run a fingertip across the spot where a placemat lives—glossy here, dull there, with a subtle ridge between. The finish is failing, and it’s happening faster than you’d like. You can feel the stakes: this is not just a table—it’s family dinners, late-night projects, first-day-of-school photos, and the clean expanse that makes a home feel ready.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/23.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>12</readingTime></item><item><title>Scuff Sand Glossy Paint To Improve Primer Adhesion</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/scuff-sand-glossy-paint-to-improve-primer-adhesion-surface-preparation/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/scuff-sand-glossy-paint-to-improve-primer-adhesion-surface-preparation/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 04:18:59 +0000</pubDate><category>Paint Removal &amp; Surface Prep</category><category>paint prep</category><category>rust removal</category><category>primer coat</category><category>sanding block</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-240</category><category>grit-320</category><category>dust control</category><description>Learn how to scuff sand glossy paint for superior primer adhesion. Step-by-step surface preparation, pro sanding tips, and clean results that last.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="surface-preparation-scuff-sand-glossy-paint-right"&gt;Surface Preparation: Scuff Sand Glossy Paint Right&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a moment every DIYer knows: coffee in hand, paint tray loaded, roller whispering across the wall—and then the dreaded slip. The glossy trim or cabinet door you thought you tamed suddenly sheds the new coat like a rain jacket, beading, sliding, or peeling on touch. I’ve been in that room more times than I can count, from weekend bathrooms to full commercial corridors, and the conclusion’s always the same—before color comes control. That control starts with surface preparation. Not flashy, not glamorous, but it’s the one step that makes every coat after it look better and last longer.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Proper Panel Degreasing Before Sanding And Painting</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/proper-panel-degreasing-before-sanding-and-painting-car-surface-prep/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/proper-panel-degreasing-before-sanding-and-painting-car-surface-prep/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:02:33 +0000</pubDate><category>Auto Body Sanding</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-600</category><category>paint prep</category><category>dust control</category><description>Learn proper panel degreasing for car surface prep: the solvents, steps, and shop tips to avoid fisheyes and get paint to stick like it should.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="car-surface-prep-proper-panel-degreasing"&gt;Car Surface Prep: Proper Panel Degreasing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, shop door cracked open, coffee perched on the fender, and a faint citrus-solvent smell in the air. That’s the moment I love most: quiet, focused, and full of possibility. You tape off the trim, set your DA sander on the cart, and reach for a clean set of nitrile gloves. If you’ve ever laid down a base coat only to watch it crater into fisheyes or peel at the edges, you know the pain of skipping a step in car surface prep. Most of the time the culprit isn’t your gun, your paint, or the weather—it’s contamination that never should have made it to the paint stage.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>Best Grit Sheets For Detail Sanding Tools</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/best-grit-sheets-for-detail-sanding-tools-detail-sander-sheets/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/best-grit-sheets-for-detail-sanding-tools-detail-sander-sheets/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 02:40:19 +0000</pubDate><category>Detail Sander Sheets</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-240</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-400</category><category>paint prep</category><description>Engineer-tested guide to detail sander sheets: grit selection, backings, dust control, and brand picks for wood, paint, and plastics.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="best-grit-detail-sander-sheets-an-engineers-guide"&gt;Best Grit Detail Sander Sheets: An Engineer’s Guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a moment in every restoration project when the big tools step aside and the small corners decide the result. I hit that moment last winter, hunched over a mid-century nightstand with tapered legs and a drawer pull recess shaped like a teardrop. My random orbit sander took care of the top in minutes, but the tight inside curves and the sharp transitions around the pull were a different story. I swapped to a detail sander and discovered what many DIYers learn the hard way: the tool is only as precise as the sheet you mount on it. The right detail sander sheets determine whether you get crisp edges and a uniform scratch or burnished tips and clogged grit.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>13</readingTime></item><item><title>What Grit To Remove Peeling Paint From Wood Trim</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/what-grit-to-remove-peeling-paint-from-wood-trim-paint-removal-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/what-grit-to-remove-peeling-paint-from-wood-trim-paint-removal-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:03:42 +0000</pubDate><category>Paint Removal &amp; Surface Prep</category><category>paint prep</category><category>rust removal</category><category>primer coat</category><category>sanding block</category><category>grit-60</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-240</category><description>Discover expert tips on paint removal sanding for wood trim. Achieve a smooth, professional finish with our step-by-step guide.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="mastering-paint-removal-sanding-for-wood-trim"&gt;Mastering Paint Removal Sanding for Wood Trim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture this: a cozy afternoon, the sun filtering through your living room windows, casting warm beams onto your worn-out wood trim. You’ve always loved the character that these old trims bring to your home, but the layers of peeling paint have long lost their charm. It’s time for a change, a revival of sorts, where the beauty of the wood can shine through once again. Whether you’re a seasoned DIY enthusiast or a curious beginner, the task of removing paint from wood trim might seem daunting. But with the right tools, grit knowledge, and a bit of patience, you can transform your trim from drab to fab, revealing its natural beauty.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>6</readingTime></item></channel></rss>