<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Between-Coats Sanding on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/categories/between-coats-sanding/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/categories/between-coats-sanding/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Remove Dust Nibs Between Clear Coat Layers</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/12/remove-dust-nibs-between-clear-coat-layers-between-coats-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/12/remove-dust-nibs-between-clear-coat-layers-between-coats-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 14:29:42 +0000</pubDate><category>Between-Coats Sanding</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-500</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-800</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>clear coat</category><category>dust control</category><category>wet sanding</category><description>Expert guide to between coats sanding—how to remove dust nibs, choose abrasives, and perfect clear coat finishes with pro-level workflows.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="between-coats-sanding-remove-dust-nibs-in-clear-coats"&gt;between coats sanding: remove dust nibs in clear coats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A flawless clear coat is more than gloss; it’s the tactile confidence you feel when your hand glides across a panel with zero grit or drag. If you’ve ever stepped back from a gorgeous piece—be it a walnut tabletop, a painted cabinet door, or a guitar body—only to see and feel the specks of dust that settled into the finish, you know the sting. Those tiny dust nibs are an inevitable reality of shop air, static, and curing dynamics. Fortunately, they’re also manageable with disciplined surface prep, controlled technique, and smart abrasive choices. That’s the core of between coats sanding: deliberate, minimal-material removal focused on de-nibbing without compromising film build or clarity.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/25.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>Best Grit For Sanding Between Coats Of Polyurethane</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/best-grit-for-sanding-between-coats-of-polyurethane-between-coats-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/best-grit-for-sanding-between-coats-of-polyurethane-between-coats-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 04:59:16 +0000</pubDate><category>Between-Coats Sanding</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-600</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><category>sanding block</category><description>Learn the best grit for sanding between coats of polyurethane, when to sand, and how to get a flawless, dust-free finish with pro-tested techniques.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="between-coats-sanding-best-grit-for-polyurethane"&gt;Between Coats Sanding: Best Grit for Polyurethane&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time you run your hand across a newly finished table and feel the faint drag of tiny dust nibs, you understand why the small steps matter. Maybe it’s a maple dining top you’ve been nursing through long evenings, or a simple pine shelf that somehow carries outsized meaning. You’ve brushed on a smooth coat, waited patiently, and yet—under a raking light—tiny specks wink back at you like a constellation you didn’t intend to draw. That’s the moment when many projects turn from “good enough” to “I want this perfect.” And the bridge to perfect is almost always between coats sanding.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>How To Scuff Sand Between Finish Coats</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/how-to-scuff-sand-between-finish-coats-between-coats-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/how-to-scuff-sand-between-finish-coats-between-coats-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 01:45:42 +0000</pubDate><category>Between-Coats Sanding</category><description>Discover the art of between coats sanding for flawless finishes. Get expert tips and step-by-step instructions for a smooth woodworking experience.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="mastering-between-coats-sanding-for-perfect-finishes"&gt;Mastering Between Coats Sanding for Perfect Finishes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture this: It’s a quiet Saturday afternoon, and the sun filters gently through your workshop window. You’re standing over a wooden table, the rich grain gleaming under a fresh coat of varnish. But you know the real magic happens between coats. That’s where the real craftsmanship lies — in the finesse of sanding between coats. This subtle yet powerful technique can transform an ordinary piece into a masterpiece, lending it a silky-smooth surface that invites touch.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>5</readingTime></item></channel></rss>