<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Waterproof &amp; Wet/Dry Paper on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/categories/waterproof--wet/dry-paper/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 15:10:10 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/categories/waterproof--wet/dry-paper/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Flush Slurry To Prevent Loading</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/16/flush-slurry-to-prevent-loading-wet-dry-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/16/flush-slurry-to-prevent-loading-wet-dry-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 15:10:09 +0000</pubDate><category>Waterproof &amp; Wet/Dry Paper</category><category>grit-280</category><category>clear coat</category><category>grit progression</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>sanding block</category><description>Learn how to flush slurry to prevent loading with wet dry sandpaper. Practical setup, rinsing, and grit strategy for cleaner, faster, longer-lasting sanding.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="flush-slurry-with-wet-dry-sandpaper-for-clean-cuts"&gt;Flush Slurry with Wet Dry Sandpaper for Clean Cuts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I noticed loading, I was hunched over a maple cutting board in a chilly garage, chasing a glass-smooth finish that never seemed to arrive. The sandpaper was supposed to be “the good stuff,” and I was stepping through the grits like a textbook. But after a few strokes, the sheet glazed over. Instead of cutting, it skated—leaving faint scorch marks and a haze of streaks. I swapped sheets, pressed harder, tried angles. Same story: the paper clogged, and the surface got warmer. That’s when the lightbulb went off. It wasn’t the grit. It wasn’t the wood. It was the slurry—swarf, resin, and water—hanging around and turning my abrasive into a slick.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/24.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>12</readingTime></item><item><title>Soap To Water Ratio For Lubrication</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/soap-to-water-ratio-for-lubrication-wet-dry-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/soap-to-water-ratio-for-lubrication-wet-dry-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 14:24:10 +0000</pubDate><category>Waterproof &amp; Wet/Dry Paper</category><category>grit-360</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-1200</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-2500</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>sanding block</category><description>Engineer-tested soap-to-water ratios for lubricating wet dry sandpaper on paint, wood, and metal. Get precise mixes, tips, and troubleshooting.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="optimal-soap-to-water-ratio-for-wet-dry-sandpaper"&gt;Optimal Soap to Water Ratio for Wet Dry Sandpaper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, a quiet garage, and a project you’ve promised yourself you’d finally finish. The headlight lenses are foggy. The table top has those telltale dust nibs in the polyurethane. A chef’s knife hangs dull on the magnetic strip, begging for bite. You fill a bucket, reach for a bottle of soap, and lay out sheets of wet dry sandpaper—ready to get to work. And then you pause. How much soap should actually go into the water? One drop? A teaspoon? More? You’ve heard “soapy water helps it glide,” but glide isn’t the only variable that matters. There’s also bite, swarf transport, scratch control, and heat. The soap-to-water ratio dictates whether you refine fast and clean—or skate on a film that kills cutting speed and blurs feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>Soak Time For Wet Sanding Papers</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/soak-time-for-wet-sanding-papers-wet-dry-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/soak-time-for-wet-sanding-papers-wet-dry-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 19:47:57 +0000</pubDate><category>Waterproof &amp; Wet/Dry Paper</category><category>grit-280</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-800</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1200</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>wet sanding</category><description>Learn the optimal soak times for wet dry sandpaper, how soaking affects abrasive performance, and precise workflows for wood, paint, and metal.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="wet-dry-sandpaper-soak-times-a-technical-guide"&gt;Wet Dry Sandpaper Soak Times: A Technical Guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shop is quiet except for the slow drip from a rinse bottle, pooling across a workbench where a clear-coated guitar body breathes under the lights. There’s a shallow tray of clean water, a few folded sheets of wet dry sandpaper, and a foam pad waiting like a promise. You press a fingertip to the lacquer—weeks of curing have left it hard, crisp, and unforgiving. You remember the last time you rushed the process and chased pigtails under a glaring shop light. Not today. Today, the water will do its work before the first stroke lands.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>12</readingTime></item></channel></rss>