<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Orbital Sander on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/tags/orbital-sander/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 04:56:41 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/tags/orbital-sander/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cut Rate And Loading Behavior By Grain</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/20/cut-rate-and-loading-behavior-by-grain-silicon-carbide-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/20/cut-rate-and-loading-behavior-by-grain-silicon-carbide-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:57:05 +0000</pubDate><category>Abrasive Materials &amp; Compounds</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-800</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><category>dry sanding</category><description>Engineer’s guide to silicon carbide sandpaper—cut rate, loading, grain physics, and practical tips to choose the right abrasive for paint, metal, and</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="silicon-carbide-sandpaper-cut-rate-and-loading"&gt;Silicon Carbide Sandpaper: Cut Rate and Loading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning in the garage, the air smelled faintly of cut clear coat and soapy water. A half-finished motorcycle tank sat on a foam cradle, its orange peel and dust nibs highlighted by a raking LED panel. I’d already tried a few sheets of 1500 grit from a contractor pack, but they stalled after a few passes, loading with milky slurry and leaving stray scratches that would require more polish later. This is the moment that separates a casual sand from a dependable workflow—the point where abrasive choice dictates not just speed, but consistency and finish quality. Swapping to silicon carbide sandpaper felt like a small change, but it reset the process: faster leveling, more controllable scratch patterns, and fewer surprise defects.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/09.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Grit Selection For Antifouling Paint Prep</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/19/grit-selection-for-antifouling-paint-prep-boat-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/19/grit-selection-for-antifouling-paint-prep-boat-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 14:20:36 +0000</pubDate><category>Marine Sanding</category><category>grit-60</category><category>grit-70</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-280</category><category>dust control</category><category>paint prep</category><category>orbital sander</category><description>Learn how to choose the right sanding grits for antifouling prep. Clear steps, pro tips, and safety for smooth, durable bottom paint results.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="boat-sanding-grit-guide-for-antifouling-prep"&gt;Boat Sanding Grit Guide for Antifouling Prep&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You feel it as soon as the travel lift sets your boat on the stands: that mix of relief and responsibility. The hull looks taller on land, the waterline a faint stain of the season gone by. There’s a quiet rhythm to the boatyard in the early hours—compressors breathe, gulls trade commentary, coffee cools beside a bucket of scrapers. You run your hand over the bottom paint and feel the story of boat sanding before you even begin: the hard, glossy ridges where the sander skipped, the chalky patches that might be underbound, the thin spots the sea worked harder than you realized. It’s tempting to rush the job and get straight to brushing on antifouling. But prep is where the next season is won. Choosing the right grit is the difference between a coat that stays put and one that blisters, powders, or peels when the boat is back in her element.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/05.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>12</readingTime></item><item><title>Multi Hole Discs Improve Airflow And Cut</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/15/multi-hole-discs-improve-airflow-and-cut-dustless-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/15/multi-hole-discs-improve-airflow-and-cut-dustless-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 14:04:48 +0000</pubDate><category>Dust Extraction Systems</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-180</category><category>joint compound</category><category>orbital sander</category><description>Learn how multi-hole discs boost airflow, cut rate, and surface finish while keeping dustless sanding clean and precise in wood, auto, and drywall jobs.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="dustless-sanding-multi-hole-discs-that-cut-faster"&gt;Dustless sanding: multi-hole discs that cut faster&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a Saturday morning in the shop, the light comes in as a hazy beam. You flip on the sander, nudge it onto an oak tabletop, and within seconds the air looks like a snow globe gone rogue. Your safety glasses fog, your shirt turns gray, and the shop vac whines like it’s doing something—but the dust still settles on every flat surface you own. I’ve been there. I’ve also watched the other version of this scene: the pad spins, dust disappears, the workpiece stays cool, and the abrasive keeps biting for pass after pass. The difference isn’t magic—it&amp;rsquo;s airflow. Specifically, the way a multi-hole disc and a properly set vacuum system handle air and debris to deliver real dustless sanding without killing your cut rate.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/16.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>Select Correct Orbit Size For Performance</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/12/select-correct-orbit-size-for-performance-random-orbital-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/12/select-correct-orbit-size-for-performance-random-orbital-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 18:01:30 +0000</pubDate><category>Random Orbital Sanding</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-220</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><description>Learn how to pick the right orbit size for random orbital sanding to boost speed, control, and surface quality, with pro tips, setups, and troubleshooting.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="random-orbital-sanding-choose-the-right-orbit-size"&gt;Random Orbital Sanding: Choose the Right Orbit Size&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s early, coffee is hot, and the workshop has that quiet hum before saws and vacs kick off. On the bench sits a maple tabletop you’ve been coaxing toward a flawless finish all week. You line up abrasives, check the vacuum hose, and reach for your sander—then pause. The sticker says 5 mm orbit, but you’ve also got a 2.5 mm model in the drawer. Which one delivers the fastest path to dead‑flat without leaving those annoying pigtails under a clear coat? This is where random orbital sanding really becomes a craft decision, not just a tool choice. Orbit size is the lever that moves your workflow. Choose it well, and you remove stock quickly, steer around swirl risks, and hit finish-quality scratch patterns faster. Choose it poorly, and you burn time, clog discs, and inherit defects you can only fix by stepping back several grits.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/29.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>How To Remove Polyurethane Or Varnish Safely From Furniture</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/10/how-to-remove-polyurethane-or-varnish-safely-from-furniture-wood-finish-removal/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/10/how-to-remove-polyurethane-or-varnish-safely-from-furniture-wood-finish-removal/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 18:54:49 +0000</pubDate><category>Furniture Refinishing</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit progression</category><category>orbital sander</category><description>Learn safe, practical wood finish removal for furniture—strip polyurethane or varnish without damage. Tools, safety, steps, tips, and troubleshooting.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="safe-wood-finish-removal-for-furniture"&gt;Safe Wood Finish Removal for Furniture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It starts as a quiet, hopeful Saturday morning. You slide open a drawer on a hand-me-down dresser and the runners squeak just slightly—an honest sound, softened by decades of use. The wood is beautiful under the glare of a shiny, ambered topcoat, but the gloss is cracked in places and the color has drifted toward orange. You imagine this piece lightened, its grain breathing again, ready for a new finish that fits your home today. There’s just one thing between you and that vision: the practical reality of wood finish removal. You’ve heard horror stories about harsh chemicals, gummy messes, and hours of sanding that erase crisp edges. You’ve also heard promises about citrus strippers and miracle gels. Somewhere between the extremes sits a safe, effective path—one that respects both your health and the furniture’s history.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>12</readingTime></item><item><title>Film Backing For Uniform Fine Scratches</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/08/film-backing-for-uniform-fine-scratches-open-coat-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/08/film-backing-for-uniform-fine-scratches-open-coat-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 13:28:53 +0000</pubDate><category>Backing Types &amp; Coatings</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-800</category><category>orbital sander</category><category>dry sanding</category><description>Engineer-tested guidance on film-backed, open coat sandpaper for uniform fine scratches, with data, setups, and grit sequencing tips.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="open-coat-sandpaper-on-film-for-fine-scratches"&gt;Open coat sandpaper on film for fine scratches&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The raking light told the truth I didn’t want to hear. After an hour shaping a walnut desktop, the surface looked perfect under diffuse shop lights—but the morning sun found every swirl and pigtail. I’d sanded carefully, stepped through grits, and kept the pad moving. Still, the micro-scratches telegraphed through as soon as I wiped on mineral spirits. That’s the moment I switched to film-backed abrasives and, crucially, open coat sandpaper for the early and mid-grits. The difference wasn’t subtle; it was measurable.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Wet Sanding To Control Marine Dust</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/08/wet-sanding-to-control-marine-dust-boat-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/08/wet-sanding-to-control-marine-dust-boat-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 00:54:10 +0000</pubDate><category>Marine Sanding</category><category>grit-60</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>orbital sander</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>sanding block</category><category>mirror finish</category><description>Learn wet boat sanding to cut toxic dust, protect waterways, and prep your hull right. Tools, grits, workflow, slurry control, and pro tips inside.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="boat-sanding-wet-techniques-to-control-marine-dust"&gt;Boat Sanding: Wet Techniques to Control Marine Dust&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a particular quiet to the yard before sunrise. The halyards ping, the coffee steams in a chipped thermos, and the hull you’ve been avoiding stands there like a promise you can’t put off. I’ve been on both sides of that moment—rushing, dusty, and regretting shortcuts later—and the method that changed the game for me was wet boat sanding. Not because it’s pretty, but because it’s efficient, safer for your lungs, and easier to keep the neighbors and the yard manager happy. You control the mess. You protect the water you love. And you end the day with a hull that’s flatter, cooler, and ready to bond.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>How To Choose A Starting Grit</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/06/how-to-choose-a-starting-grit-sandpaper-grit-chart/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/06/how-to-choose-a-starting-grit-sandpaper-grit-chart/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 15:25:52 +0000</pubDate><category>Grit Guide &amp; Education</category><category>grit chart</category><category>abrasive standards</category><category>grit progression</category><category>grit-60</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-101</category><category>grit-120</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><description>Learn how to choose your starting grit with a clear sandpaper grit chart, shop-tested sequences, and pro tips for clean, fast, and flat sanding.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="sandpaper-grit-chart-choose-the-right-starting-grit"&gt;Sandpaper Grit Chart: Choose the Right Starting Grit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I watched a flawless finish come alive, it happened in the last ten minutes of a long Saturday in the shop. Cold radio in the background, dust collector humming, I wiped a splash of mineral spirits across a dining tabletop and the grain popped like a film reveal. That moment didn’t come from luck—it came from choosing the right starting grit. I keep a small sandpaper grit chart taped to my cabinet door, not because I can’t memorize grits, but because the surface in front of you changes the rules. A hundred-year-old oak stained dark is not the same as new maple fresh off the planer. Paint sprayed last month is not like six coats of hand-brushed oil from the 90s. The trick is reading the job, then picking the grit that does the heavy lifting without making more work.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Choose Hose Diameter For Best Suction</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/06/choose-hose-diameter-for-best-suction-dustless-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/06/choose-hose-diameter-for-best-suction-dustless-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 14:24:00 +0000</pubDate><category>Dust Extraction Systems</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-120</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>orbital sander</category><category>sanding block</category><category>joint compound</category><description>An engineer’s guide to hose diameter for dustless sanding—get the best suction, cleaner air, and faster finishing with data-driven choices.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="dustless-sanding-pick-the-right-hose-diameter"&gt;Dustless Sanding: Pick the Right Hose Diameter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I tried to sand a maple tabletop in my small garage, I didn’t plan for the dust. Within minutes, a visible cloud hovered over my workbench, the air had that chalky taste, and the light from the door turned into a foggy beam. The sander did its job, but the shop felt uninhabitable. Fast-forward to today, and my setup looks completely different: a quiet extractor hums under the bench, a smooth-bore hose clips into a sander with a snug port connection, and the cleanup is mostly emptying a bag. The shift to dustless sanding wasn’t just about comfort—it was about control. Once you understand how hose diameter, hose length, and vacuum performance interact, you can tune a system that captures chips and submicron dust instead of aerosolizing it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Difference Between Da And Random Orbital Sanding</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/difference-between-da-and-random-orbital-sanding-random-orbital-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/difference-between-da-and-random-orbital-sanding-random-orbital-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 13:35:28 +0000</pubDate><category>Random Orbital Sanding</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-240</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-400</category><category>dust control</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><description>An engineer’s guide to the difference between DA and random orbital sanding, with test-based advice on speed, finish, abrasives, and setup.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="da-vs-random-orbital-sanding-an-engineers-guide"&gt;DA vs random orbital sanding: an engineer’s guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning in the shop, the kettle clicks off as the garage door rolls up and a slab of maple waits on the sawhorses. The winter light is unforgiving; it shows every swirl that last year’s “good enough” sanding left behind. In one hand: a well-balanced 5-inch palm sander; in the other: a heavier, gear-driven unit that can bulldoze epoxy ridges like a planer. The decision—random orbital sanding or the so-called DA—doesn’t feel philosophical. It’s practical. Do I want a fast, aggressive cut to level those glue lines, or a controlled, low-risk finish for the final passes? If you’ve ever chased phantom swirls under a bright lamp or watched edges burn through because you leaned a degree too far, you know the stakes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Sic Versus Aluminum Oxide Differences</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/sic-versus-aluminum-oxide-differences-silicon-carbide-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/sic-versus-aluminum-oxide-differences-silicon-carbide-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 02:51:33 +0000</pubDate><category>Abrasive Materials &amp; Compounds</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><category>sanding block</category><description>Compare silicon carbide sandpaper and aluminum oxide to choose the right abrasive for wood, metal, and paint. Clear, practical tips for better finishes.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="silicon-carbide-sandpaper-vs-aluminum-oxide-guide"&gt;Silicon Carbide Sandpaper vs Aluminum Oxide Guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a quiet Saturday afternoon, you clamp down the last door of that heirloom dresser you’ve been restoring. The grain finally shows through the old varnish, but the surface still isn’t the mirror-smooth finish you pictured. You reach for a fresh sheet, feel the grit with your thumb, and hesitate—this is where the choice between silicon carbide sandpaper and aluminum oxide decides whether you’ll spend the evening admiring your work or chasing scratches you didn’t mean to make. Maybe you’re here because a paint finish went cloudy after dry sanding, or a clear coat took a hopscotch of swirls under shop lights. Or maybe your belt sander chewed through hook-and-loop discs like a wood chipper and you need something tougher and more predictable.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>13</readingTime></item><item><title>When Ceramic Outperforms Aluminum Oxide</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/when-ceramic-outperforms-aluminum-oxide-ceramic-sanding-discs/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/when-ceramic-outperforms-aluminum-oxide-ceramic-sanding-discs/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 13:34:14 +0000</pubDate><category>Ceramic &amp; Premium Abrasives</category><category>grit-60</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-180</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><category>dust control</category><description>Learn when ceramic sanding discs beat aluminum oxide: cut rate, heat control, cost per part, and pro tips for metal, wood, and composites.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="when-ceramic-sanding-discs-outperform-aluminum-oxide"&gt;When Ceramic Sanding Discs Outperform Aluminum Oxide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a quiet Saturday morning, the garage becomes your studio. You’ve cleared a workbench, lined up clamps and rags, and lit the space with a warm shop lamp. The project is personal: a welded steel coffee table for the living room, something sturdy and simple that can hold the weight of everyday life. The first passes with a grinder feel hopeful—until the discs start glazing. Heat builds, paint smears, and the cut slows to a crawl. You switch to a finer grit, then back again, but the aluminum oxide discs keep dulling, forcing you to lean harder. The surface looks scuffed but not flat, and your shoulders ache from forcing the tool to do what the abrasive simply won’t.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Velcro Disc Attachment For Orbital Sanders</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/velcro-disc-attachment-for-orbital-sanders-hook-and-loop-sanding-discs/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/velcro-disc-attachment-for-orbital-sanders-hook-and-loop-sanding-discs/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 04:51:13 +0000</pubDate><category>Hook-and-Loop Discs</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-240</category><category>grit-320</category><category>orbital sander</category><description>Engineer-tested guide to hook and loop sanding discs, from pad heat and disc selection to failure modes, setup tips, and performance tests.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="hook-and-loop-sanding-discs-for-orbital-sanders"&gt;Hook and Loop Sanding Discs for Orbital Sanders&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Saturday morning in the shop starts with optimism—the kind that comes with fresh coffee, a new sheet of maple, and the subtle hum of a random orbital sander spooling up. Ten minutes later, optimism hits the floor with the sanding disc. If you’ve been there, you know the feeling: the Velcro-style backing is glazed, the pad hooks are shiny and rounded over, and every new disc lasts a little shorter than the last. The culprit isn’t just cheap consumables; more often it’s heat, pressure, and a mismatch between tool, pad, and abrasive. This is where hook and loop sanding discs earn both their reputation for convenience and the blame when the system isn’t set up correctly.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>15</readingTime></item><item><title>Prevent Swirl Marks With Random Orbital Sanders</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/prevent-swirl-marks-with-random-orbital-sanders-random-orbital-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/prevent-swirl-marks-with-random-orbital-sanders-random-orbital-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 02:33:16 +0000</pubDate><category>Random Orbital Sanding</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-800</category><category>dust control</category><category>grit progression</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><description>Learn expert workflows to eliminate swirl marks with random orbital sanding—covering surface prep, abrasives, dust control, and inspection.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="prevent-swirl-marks-with-random-orbital-sanding"&gt;Prevent Swirl Marks with Random Orbital Sanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, low sun at the window, the first coat of finish flashes across the panel you’ve been nursing all week. The figure in the oak wakes up, but so do faint halos you didn’t see under shop lights. Swirl marks. You tilt the board, squint, and realize you were moments from locking those defects under a film for good. It’s a gut-punch that most woodworkers and finish carpenters eventually feel. The culprit is rarely the tool itself; it’s the stack of process decisions that lead to one outcome or the other. The relief is that processes are controllable, and with random orbital sanding done deliberately, swirls are optional.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>13</readingTime></item></channel></rss>