<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Hand Sanding Techniques on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/categories/hand-sanding-techniques/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/categories/hand-sanding-techniques/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Choose Sanding Direction To Follow The Grain</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/09/choose-sanding-direction-to-follow-the-grain-hand-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/09/choose-sanding-direction-to-follow-the-grain-hand-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 18:57:00 +0000</pubDate><category>Hand Sanding Techniques</category><category>grit-60</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-500</category><description>Learn how to choose sanding direction, optimize abrasive performance, and master hand sanding workflows for flawless, grain-aligned wood surfaces.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="hand-sanding-with-the-grain-direction-that-wins"&gt;Hand Sanding With the Grain: Direction That Wins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first pass across the old walnut dresser felt almost sacrilegious. Early light from the shop window caught the cathedral patterns in the veneer and made the scratches I’d inherited glow silver against the warm brown. Years of hasty refinishes had left low, cross-grain swirls that refused to disappear under fresh film. I set the random-orbit sander aside, reached for a cork block, and let the board tell me where it wanted me to go. In that moment, hand sanding was not about nostalgia—it was about control. Fingers learned the flow of the fibers, eyes trained on the raking light, strokes tracking the grain like a compass needle finally finding north.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>12</readingTime></item><item><title>How To Sand Wood By Hand For Smooth Finish</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/how-to-sand-wood-by-hand-for-smooth-finish-hand-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/how-to-sand-wood-by-hand-for-smooth-finish-hand-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 03:41:00 +0000</pubDate><category>Hand Sanding Techniques</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>sanding block</category><category>grit progression</category><category>dry sanding</category><description>Learn hand sanding techniques, grit progression, and pro tips to achieve a flawless smooth wood finish with clear steps, tools, and troubleshooting.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="hand-sanding-for-a-glass-smooth-wood-finish"&gt;Hand sanding for a glass-smooth wood finish&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a quiet Saturday morning, the house is still enough to hear the tiny rasp of paper against wood. Sunlight falls across the table you’ve promised to restore—the one that’s been gathering keys, grocery bags, and happy-hour mail for years. At first glance, it seems fine. But run your fingertips from the center to the edge and you can feel a map of dents, glue drips, and faint chatter lines left by the last sander. This is where patience matters. This is where hand sanding earns its reputation.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item></channel></rss>