<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Grit-1000 on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/tags/grit-1000/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 05:56:37 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/tags/grit-1000/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Compound Versus Polish Differences For Clear Coat Finishing</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/11/compound-versus-polish-differences-for-clear-coat-finishing-paint-polishing/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/11/compound-versus-polish-differences-for-clear-coat-finishing-paint-polishing/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 05:56:37 +0000</pubDate><category>Wet Sanding Clear Coat</category><category>grit-800</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-2500</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>clear coat</category><category>wet sanding</category><description>Understand compound vs polish for clear coat finishing with sanding workflows, abrasive selection, and process control for defect-free paint polishing.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="paint-polishing-compound-vs-polish-for-clear-coat"&gt;Paint polishing: compound vs polish for clear coat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Saturday morning sun can be the most unforgiving inspector you’ll ever meet. You back the car out after a late-night respray—coffee in hand, optimism high—and the light slices across the hood like a straightedge. Orange peel you knew about, sure. But then the swirls appear, whisper-fine arcs barely visible at dusk now glaring at full volume. You feel them before you see them: the drag of a microfiber catching on texture, the way your eyes follow a ghosty hologram around a curved fender. This is the moment when “wash and wax” ends and craft begins—where surface preparation, abrasive control, and paint polishing decide whether you get a mirror or a mirage.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/17.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>Wet Sanding To Control Marine Dust</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/08/wet-sanding-to-control-marine-dust-boat-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/08/wet-sanding-to-control-marine-dust-boat-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 00:54:10 +0000</pubDate><category>Marine Sanding</category><category>grit-60</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>orbital sander</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>sanding block</category><category>mirror finish</category><description>Learn wet boat sanding to cut toxic dust, protect waterways, and prep your hull right. Tools, grits, workflow, slurry control, and pro tips inside.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="boat-sanding-wet-techniques-to-control-marine-dust"&gt;Boat Sanding: Wet Techniques to Control Marine Dust&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a particular quiet to the yard before sunrise. The halyards ping, the coffee steams in a chipped thermos, and the hull you’ve been avoiding stands there like a promise you can’t put off. I’ve been on both sides of that moment—rushing, dusty, and regretting shortcuts later—and the method that changed the game for me was wet boat sanding. Not because it’s pretty, but because it’s efficient, safer for your lungs, and easier to keep the neighbors and the yard manager happy. You control the mess. You protect the water you love. And you end the day with a hull that’s flatter, cooler, and ready to bond.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>Progressive Micron Steps For Clarity</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/08/progressive-micron-steps-for-clarity-glass-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/08/progressive-micron-steps-for-clarity-glass-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 00:41:16 +0000</pubDate><category>Glass &amp; Ceramics Sanding</category><category>grit-60</category><category>grit-500</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>dry sanding</category><description>Engineer-tested guide to glass sanding using progressive micron steps for optical clarity, with media choices, wet technique, and polishing workflow.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="glass-sanding-progressive-micron-steps-for-clarity"&gt;Glass Sanding: Progressive Micron Steps for Clarity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You notice it first at breakfast—the way the morning light breaks into a haze across your coffee table. A scratch the length of a paperclip sits dead center, scattering highlights into a milky halo that wasn’t there last week. You run a fingernail across it. The catch is slight, but it’s there. It’s the same story with a watch crystal that met a brick wall one hurried afternoon, or a window panel that’s accumulated fine swirls from years of cleaning. Replacing glass is one option, but it’s expensive, wasteful, and impractical for built-ins. As a product engineer who spends an unreasonable amount of time testing abrasives, I prefer another route: controlled, progressive glass sanding that restores optical clarity rather than hides damage.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Remove 1500–2000 Grit Marks On Resin</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/remove-1500-2000-grit-marks-on-resin-resin-polishing/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/remove-1500-2000-grit-marks-on-resin-resin-polishing/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 23:56:25 +0000</pubDate><category>Resin Polishing</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1200</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-2500</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>dust control</category><description>Expert workflows to remove 1500–2000 grit marks on resin and achieve optical clarity with the right abrasives, compounds, and heat control.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="resin-polishing-erasing-15002000-grit-scratches"&gt;Resin Polishing: Erasing 1500–2000 Grit Scratches&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pendant looked flawless on the bench last night—glassy, color suspended in amber, edges softened just so. Then morning light hit it. Under a low-angle window beam, micro-scratches flared across the surface like frost on a windshield. You could feel your shoulders sag. You did the careful wet-sand through 1500 and 2000, kept the strokes even, swirled the slurry away. It should be done. But resin is unforgiving under raking light, and 1500–2000 grit marks hang on, whisper-thin but brutally visible. This is the moment where the craft turns from “sanding” to resin polishing: closing the cut, controlling heat, and stepping the abrasive system with intent until the surface stops being a surface and becomes a reflection.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>9</readingTime></item><item><title>Let Epoxy Cure Fully Before Sanding</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/let-epoxy-cure-fully-before-sanding-epoxy-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/let-epoxy-cure-fully-before-sanding-epoxy-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 16:25:05 +0000</pubDate><category>Plastic &amp; Epoxy Sanding</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-360</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit progression</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>dry sanding</category><description>Learn why letting epoxy fully cure before sanding is essential, plus timelines, tests, grit progressions, and pro tips for flawless, clear finishes.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="epoxy-sanding-why-waiting-to-cure-pays-off"&gt;Epoxy Sanding: Why Waiting to Cure Pays Off&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a point in every resin project when anticipation and restraint collide. You’ve de‑molded a river board you poured last weekend or set down a glossy flood coat on a tabletop, and the surface is whispering promises of glass-like clarity. You picture the final reveal: the light catching the grain, the resin depth turning everyday moments into a small ceremony. You also see the last mile between what is and what could be—the smoothing, refining, and polishing phase—also known as epoxy sanding. Your hands ache to pick up the sander. But this is where patience protects your craftsmanship.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Keep Surfaces Flat With Rigid Blocks</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/keep-surfaces-flat-with-rigid-blocks-sanding-block/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/keep-surfaces-flat-with-rigid-blocks-sanding-block/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 15:23:32 +0000</pubDate><category>Sanding Blocks</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>sanding block</category><description>Learn how rigid sanding blocks keep surfaces flat, when to use them, and the techniques, materials, and tips that deliver flawless, true results.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="keep-surfaces-flat-with-a-rigid-sanding-block"&gt;Keep Surfaces Flat with a Rigid Sanding Block&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a moment in any refinishing project when your eye catches the light just right and you see it: subtle waves in a tabletop, a faint ripple in primer, a break in the reflections across a glossy guitar body. You feel it with your fingertips too—those barely-there rises and dips that make the difference between “good enough” and “crafted.” I remember the first time I noticed how my results changed when I switched from a soft pad to a rigid sanding block. The surface I thought was “close” suddenly told the truth. Within a few careful passes, the highs dulled evenly and the lows showed as untouched pencil marks. In minutes, the surface was flatter than I’d ever achieved before.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>13</readingTime></item><item><title>Best Wet Sanding Sequence For Plastic Headlight Lenses</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/best-wet-sanding-sequence-for-plastic-headlight-lenses-lens-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/best-wet-sanding-sequence-for-plastic-headlight-lenses-lens-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 03:51:43 +0000</pubDate><category>Headlight Restoration</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-800</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1200</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-2500</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>dry sanding</category><description>A precise, technical guide to wet lens sanding for plastic headlights—abrasives, workflows, and UV protection to restore clear, durable optics.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="best-lens-sanding-sequence-for-plastic-headlights"&gt;Best Lens Sanding Sequence for Plastic Headlights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twilight is the worst time to discover your headlights are lying to you. Streetlights smear into blurry halos; lane markers fade into a matte wash. You feel yourself leaning forward in the seat as if posture could coax more lumens from the housings. But the problem isn’t the bulb; it’s the lens. Polycarbonate oxidizes, turns porous, and grows a diffuse surface that scatters light instead of transmitting it. That’s fixable if you stop thinking of restoration as a wipe-on miracle and start treating it like precision surface engineering. This guide is about real lens sanding—structured, wet, and sequential—not guessing with a single pad until it “looks better.”&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>How To Repair Chipped Or Lifting Veneer Before Refinishing</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/how-to-repair-chipped-or-lifting-veneer-before-refinishing-furniture-restoration/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/how-to-repair-chipped-or-lifting-veneer-before-refinishing-furniture-restoration/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 15:40:12 +0000</pubDate><category>Furniture Refinishing</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-1000</category><description>Learn how to repair chipped or lifting veneer before refinishing. A pro’s step-by-step furniture restoration guide with tools, glue choices, and sanding tips.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="furniture-restoration-fixing-chipped-and-lifting-veneer"&gt;Furniture Restoration: Fixing Chipped and Lifting Veneer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, shop lights warm, coffee cooling on the bench. I slide a hand over a walnut dresser that’s outlived two generations. It has presence—clean lines, true drawers, the kind of proportions you can’t fake—but the veneer tells a rougher story. One front edge is chipped back to the substrate. A corner has lifted into a sharp little tent. Water once sat beneath a pot, raising a blister the size of a thumb. You could pass this piece over at a thrift store and never know what it could become. Or you can see it for what it is: a solid candidate for furniture restoration with a few smart, careful veneer repairs.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>12</readingTime></item><item><title>Raise The Grain With Water Before Final Sanding</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/raise-the-grain-with-water-before-final-sanding-grain-preparation/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/raise-the-grain-with-water-before-final-sanding-grain-preparation/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 13:36:49 +0000</pubDate><category>Wood sanding</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit progression</category><description>Engineer-tested methods for grain preparation: why wet-raising wood before final sanding improves stain uniformity and surface smoothness.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="grain-preparation-raise-the-grain-before-final-sanding"&gt;Grain Preparation: Raise the Grain Before Final Sanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I watched a walnut tabletop go from silky-smooth to prickly in minutes, I winced. I had sanded carefully through the grits, vacuumed, inspected under raking light—then I misted it with water. Within ten minutes, tiny “whiskers” stood up across the surface like a five o’clock shadow. If you’re new to this, the instinct is to panic. But as a product engineer who spends days measuring scratch patterns, fiber deformation, and finish adhesion, I’ve learned that moment is when control begins. What looks like backtracking is actually the most reliable path to a level, refined finish. It’s the heart of grain preparation.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>12</readingTime></item><item><title>How To Sand Wood By Hand For Smooth Finish</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/how-to-sand-wood-by-hand-for-smooth-finish-hand-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/how-to-sand-wood-by-hand-for-smooth-finish-hand-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 03:41:00 +0000</pubDate><category>Hand Sanding Techniques</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>sanding block</category><category>grit progression</category><category>dry sanding</category><description>Learn hand sanding techniques, grit progression, and pro tips to achieve a flawless smooth wood finish with clear steps, tools, and troubleshooting.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="hand-sanding-for-a-glass-smooth-wood-finish"&gt;Hand sanding for a glass-smooth wood finish&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a quiet Saturday morning, the house is still enough to hear the tiny rasp of paper against wood. Sunlight falls across the table you’ve promised to restore—the one that’s been gathering keys, grocery bags, and happy-hour mail for years. At first glance, it seems fine. But run your fingertips from the center to the edge and you can feel a map of dents, glue drips, and faint chatter lines left by the last sander. This is where patience matters. This is where hand sanding earns its reputation.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Sic Versus Aluminum Oxide Differences</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/sic-versus-aluminum-oxide-differences-silicon-carbide-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/sic-versus-aluminum-oxide-differences-silicon-carbide-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 02:51:33 +0000</pubDate><category>Abrasive Materials &amp; Compounds</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><category>sanding block</category><description>Compare silicon carbide sandpaper and aluminum oxide to choose the right abrasive for wood, metal, and paint. Clear, practical tips for better finishes.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="silicon-carbide-sandpaper-vs-aluminum-oxide-guide"&gt;Silicon Carbide Sandpaper vs Aluminum Oxide Guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a quiet Saturday afternoon, you clamp down the last door of that heirloom dresser you’ve been restoring. The grain finally shows through the old varnish, but the surface still isn’t the mirror-smooth finish you pictured. You reach for a fresh sheet, feel the grit with your thumb, and hesitate—this is where the choice between silicon carbide sandpaper and aluminum oxide decides whether you’ll spend the evening admiring your work or chasing scratches you didn’t mean to make. Maybe you’re here because a paint finish went cloudy after dry sanding, or a clear coat took a hopscotch of swirls under shop lights. Or maybe your belt sander chewed through hook-and-loop discs like a wood chipper and you need something tougher and more predictable.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>13</readingTime></item><item><title>Progress From Metal Bond To Resin Pads</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/progress-from-metal-bond-to-resin-pads-concrete-polishing/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/progress-from-metal-bond-to-resin-pads-concrete-polishing/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 01:54:08 +0000</pubDate><category>Stone &amp; Concrete Polishing</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit progression</category><description>Learn how to progress from metal bond to resin pads in concrete polishing with clear grit sequences, on-site tips, and pro workflows that deliver mirror</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="concrete-polishing-metal-to-resin-pad-mastery"&gt;Concrete Polishing: Metal to Resin Pad Mastery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a moment in every shop or garage when the floor starts to tell your story. Early morning light spills under the door; you flick on the grinder, and the air lifts just a little with the smell of damp concrete and sawdust from yesterday’s build. You set your coffee down, lace up, and eye the slab—dusty in patches, shiny where years of foot traffic have burnished a path to your bench. This is where concrete polishing earns its keep. It’s not just about gloss. It’s about turning a stained, work-weary surface into a durable, cleanable plane that makes every task feel smoother. And like any good build, the finish depends on the foundation: the right tools, the right sequence, and the discipline to switch from metal to resin at the exact right moment.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>15</readingTime></item><item><title>Polish Epoxy Resin To Glass Like Finish</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/polish-epoxy-resin-to-glass-like-finish-resin-polishing/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/polish-epoxy-resin-to-glass-like-finish-resin-polishing/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 21:00:08 +0000</pubDate><category>Resin Polishing</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-800</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1500</category><description>Learn how to polish epoxy resin to a glass-like finish with step-by-step sanding, heat control, compounds, and pro tips for durable clarity.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="resin-polishing-for-a-glass-like-epoxy-finish"&gt;Resin Polishing for a Glass-Like Epoxy Finish&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time you run a fingertip across an epoxy surface, it’s a little magic trick. The light catches, colors bloom, and you expect the kind of clarity you see on showroom glass. But if you’ve poured, leveled, and cured resin yourself, you also know the moment that follows: under sunlight or a raking lamp, faint haze, scratch patterns, or tiny undulations whisper that the job isn’t quite done. That’s where resonant craftsmanship meets patience—where resin polishing turns a good pour into a gleaming, glass-like finish.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>14</readingTime></item><item><title>Soak Time For Wet Sanding Papers</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/soak-time-for-wet-sanding-papers-wet-dry-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/soak-time-for-wet-sanding-papers-wet-dry-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 19:47:57 +0000</pubDate><category>Waterproof &amp; Wet/Dry Paper</category><category>grit-280</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-800</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1200</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>wet sanding</category><description>Learn the optimal soak times for wet dry sandpaper, how soaking affects abrasive performance, and precise workflows for wood, paint, and metal.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="wet-dry-sandpaper-soak-times-a-technical-guide"&gt;Wet Dry Sandpaper Soak Times: A Technical Guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shop is quiet except for the slow drip from a rinse bottle, pooling across a workbench where a clear-coated guitar body breathes under the lights. There’s a shallow tray of clean water, a few folded sheets of wet dry sandpaper, and a foam pad waiting like a promise. You press a fingertip to the lacquer—weeks of curing have left it hard, crisp, and unforgiving. You remember the last time you rushed the process and chased pigtails under a glaring shop light. Not today. Today, the water will do its work before the first stroke lands.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>12</readingTime></item><item><title>Difference Between Compounding And Polishing</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/difference-between-compounding-and-polishing-polishing-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/difference-between-compounding-and-polishing-polishing-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 02:16:29 +0000</pubDate><category>Polishing &amp; Finishing</category><category>mirror finish</category><category>polishing pads</category><category>grit progression</category><category>grit-800</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1200</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>clear coat</category><description>Learn the difference between compounding and polishing, how to choose polishing sandpaper and pads, and the step-by-step process for flawless finishes.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="compounding-vs-polishing-guide-to-polishing-sandpaper"&gt;Compounding vs Polishing: Guide to Polishing Sandpaper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a moment every craftsperson recognizes: you step into the garage or studio, sunlight cuts across a painted panel or tabletop, and you see everything—swirls you never meant to leave, scratches that catch the light just so, a haze that dulls the color you spent hours applying. Your instinct might be to reach for the strongest product you own, but knowing the difference between compounding and polishing—and where polishing sandpaper fits—can save time, material, and the finish you’re trying to protect. Maybe it’s the clear coat on your daily driver, the lacquer on a guitar body, or the resin on a turned pen blank. Different surfaces, same goal: remove defects while preserving as much material as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item></channel></rss>