<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Floor &amp; Deck Sanding on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/categories/floor--deck-sanding/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 21:54:28 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/categories/floor--deck-sanding/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Moisture And Acclimation Checks Before Floor Sanding</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/10/moisture-and-acclimation-checks-before-floor-sanding-wood-floor-prep/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/10/moisture-and-acclimation-checks-before-floor-sanding-wood-floor-prep/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 21:54:27 +0000</pubDate><category>Floor &amp; Deck Sanding</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-220</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>grit progression</category><description>Moisture and acclimation checks for wood floor prep. Learn how to test, stabilize, and time sanding for flat, durable finishes and zero surprises.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="wood-floor-prep-moisture-and-acclimation-before-sanding"&gt;Wood floor prep: moisture and acclimation before sanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I heard a moisture meter beep in an empty living room, I knew my weekend “quick sand and coat” wasn’t going to be quick at all. Sunlight was warming the boards by the patio door, the HVAC was off to save a few bucks, and the floor felt flat. But wood doesn’t ask how it feels—it tells you through movement. That morning, I leaned on the handle of my drum sander and thought about the real beginning of any wood floor prep: knowing where the moisture sits, where it’s heading, and whether the room’s climate matches the life the floor will live after you’re done. If you’ve ever watched stain turn blotchy, or a new finish develop white lines at board edges, you’ve met moisture the hard way.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/13.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Best Grit For Deck Sanding Before Staining</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/best-grit-for-deck-sanding-before-staining-deck-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/best-grit-for-deck-sanding-before-staining-deck-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 19:32:49 +0000</pubDate><category>Floor &amp; Deck Sanding</category><category>grit-60</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-320</category><category>deck sanding</category><category>grit progression</category><description>Engineer-tested guide to the best grit for deck sanding before staining, with abrasive science, tool choices, and proven sanding sequences.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="best-grit-for-deck-sanding-before-staining"&gt;Best Grit for Deck Sanding Before Staining&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning sunlight hits the deck and it looks like two decks at once: the cheerful gathering place you want for the season ahead, and the weathered surface you’ve come to ignore—grayed, patchy stain, a couple of raised splinters in the traffic lane from the back door. If you’ve decided to refresh it, you’ll run into a deceptively technical question right away: what’s the best grit for deck sanding before staining? As a product engineer who field-tests tools and abrasives, I’ve learned that grit choice isn’t a cosmetic preference—it’s a performance variable that decides how well stain bonds, how evenly it soaks, and how long your finish resists UV and foot traffic. In deck sanding, you aren’t polishing furniture; you’re tuning the surface profile to balance penetration and smoothness.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Best Grit Sequence For Hardwood Floor Sanding</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/02/best-grit-sequence-for-hardwood-floor-sanding-floor-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/02/best-grit-sequence-for-hardwood-floor-sanding-floor-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 21:13:10 +0000</pubDate><category>Floor &amp; Deck Sanding</category><category>grit progression</category><description>Discover the ultimate grit sequence for hardwood floor sanding to achieve smooth, professional results in your DIY projects.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="best-grit-sequence-for-hardwood-floor-sanding"&gt;Best Grit Sequence for Hardwood Floor Sanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine the feeling of walking into your living room and seeing the impeccable finish of a newly sanded hardwood floor. The light dances off the smooth surface, and the warmth of the wood invites you to sink your toes into its natural beauty. This transformation isn&amp;rsquo;t just a dream; it&amp;rsquo;s a reality you can achieve with the right knowledge and tools. Floor sanding is an art that can elevate the aesthetic of any space, whether you&amp;rsquo;re a DIY enthusiast or a seasoned professional. The secret lies in mastering the grit sequence, a crucial component that determines the outcome of your sanding project.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>5</readingTime></item></channel></rss>