<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Eco &amp; Non-Toxic Abrasives on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/categories/eco--non-toxic-abrasives/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 13:28:16 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/categories/eco--non-toxic-abrasives/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dust Reduction Strategies During Sanding</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/09/dust-reduction-strategies-during-sanding-eco-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/09/dust-reduction-strategies-during-sanding-eco-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 13:28:15 +0000</pubDate><category>Eco &amp; Non-Toxic Abrasives</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-400</category><category>dust control</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>grit progression</category><description>Cut dust at the source with smart sanding tactics, from vacuums and eco sandpaper to room containment and cleanup. Clear steps for cleaner, safer projects.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="eco-sandpaper-and-dust-free-sanding-strategies"&gt;Eco sandpaper and dust-free sanding strategies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time you notice sanding dust is rarely at the tool. It’s later—when the afternoon light cuts across the room and reveals a fine, floating galaxy you didn’t know you’d made. It settles on window sills and picture frames, drifts into the next room, and somehow finds its way into the keyboard you swear you covered. If you’re working in a small shop or a spare bedroom, those particles don’t just make a mess; they linger in the air you breathe, polish themselves into a film on every surface, and complicate the finish you apply next. It’s a familiar scene to anyone who’s refinished a table, resurfaced a stair tread, or prepped cabinet doors on a weekend. The surprise is not how fast dust spreads—it’s how persistent it is once you let it escape.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>12</readingTime></item><item><title>Low Voc Binder Options For Abrasives</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/low-voc-binder-options-for-abrasives-eco-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/low-voc-binder-options-for-abrasives-eco-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 03:24:31 +0000</pubDate><category>Eco &amp; Non-Toxic Abrasives</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-240</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-800</category><category>sanding block</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><description>Low-VOC binder guide for eco sandpaper: materials, performance tradeoffs, and a step-by-step shop workflow for cleaner, pro-grade sanding.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="eco-sandpaper-low-voc-binder-options-that-work"&gt;Eco Sandpaper: Low-VOC Binder Options That Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know that smell the minute you crack open the shop on a warm morning—the stale bite of solvents baked into the air, the stuff that lingers in your nose long after the last pass with the sanding block. That’s the old world of abrasives talking. As a cabinetmaker turned workshop coach, I’ve logged hundreds of hours testing sheets, belts, and discs that either left my head buzzing or my surfaces butter-smooth. These days, the best of both worlds is real: low-VOC binders in eco sandpaper that can hold grit like a bulldog, resist loading, and let you breathe easier in a small shop without a giant extractor humming all day.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>12</readingTime></item></channel></rss>