<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Abrasive Materials &amp; Compounds on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/categories/abrasive-materials--compounds/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 04:40:47 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/categories/abrasive-materials--compounds/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cut Rate And Loading Behavior By Grain</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/20/cut-rate-and-loading-behavior-by-grain-silicon-carbide-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/20/cut-rate-and-loading-behavior-by-grain-silicon-carbide-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:57:05 +0000</pubDate><category>Abrasive Materials &amp; Compounds</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-800</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>grit-3000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><category>dry sanding</category><description>Engineer’s guide to silicon carbide sandpaper—cut rate, loading, grain physics, and practical tips to choose the right abrasive for paint, metal, and</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="silicon-carbide-sandpaper-cut-rate-and-loading"&gt;Silicon Carbide Sandpaper: Cut Rate and Loading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning in the garage, the air smelled faintly of cut clear coat and soapy water. A half-finished motorcycle tank sat on a foam cradle, its orange peel and dust nibs highlighted by a raking LED panel. I’d already tried a few sheets of 1500 grit from a contractor pack, but they stalled after a few passes, loading with milky slurry and leaving stray scratches that would require more polish later. This is the moment that separates a casual sand from a dependable workflow—the point where abrasive choice dictates not just speed, but consistency and finish quality. Swapping to silicon carbide sandpaper felt like a small change, but it reset the process: faster leveling, more controllable scratch patterns, and fewer surprise defects.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/09.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>When To Choose Ceramic Over Sic</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/08/when-to-choose-ceramic-over-sic-silicon-carbide-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/08/when-to-choose-ceramic-over-sic-silicon-carbide-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 02:26:28 +0000</pubDate><category>Abrasive Materials &amp; Compounds</category><category>grit-60</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-240</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-800</category><description>Learn when ceramic abrasives outperform silicon carbide sandpaper for metals, composites, and coatings, with actionable workflows and pro surface-prep tips.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="choosing-ceramic-vs-silicon-carbide-sandpaper"&gt;Choosing Ceramic vs Silicon Carbide Sandpaper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can hear it before you see it: the sander spins up, the deck light pools across a panel, and the first passes scratch a story into the surface. On a chilly Saturday morning, I’m in a small body shop with two stacks on the cart—one ceramic-oxide disc set, one pile of silicon carbide sandpaper sheets. The job is a split personality: strip rust from a welded bracket, level high-build primer on a fender, then color-sand a fresh clear coat. The wrong abrasive wastes time and ruins finish; the right abrasive turns minutes into clean geometry and predictable gloss. And the smartest choice changes as the substrate, coating, and workflow change.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Sic Versus Aluminum Oxide Differences</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/sic-versus-aluminum-oxide-differences-silicon-carbide-sandpaper/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/04/sic-versus-aluminum-oxide-differences-silicon-carbide-sandpaper/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 02:51:33 +0000</pubDate><category>Abrasive Materials &amp; Compounds</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-1000</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><category>sanding block</category><description>Compare silicon carbide sandpaper and aluminum oxide to choose the right abrasive for wood, metal, and paint. Clear, practical tips for better finishes.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="silicon-carbide-sandpaper-vs-aluminum-oxide-guide"&gt;Silicon Carbide Sandpaper vs Aluminum Oxide Guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a quiet Saturday afternoon, you clamp down the last door of that heirloom dresser you’ve been restoring. The grain finally shows through the old varnish, but the surface still isn’t the mirror-smooth finish you pictured. You reach for a fresh sheet, feel the grit with your thumb, and hesitate—this is where the choice between silicon carbide sandpaper and aluminum oxide decides whether you’ll spend the evening admiring your work or chasing scratches you didn’t mean to make. Maybe you’re here because a paint finish went cloudy after dry sanding, or a clear coat took a hopscotch of swirls under shop lights. Or maybe your belt sander chewed through hook-and-loop discs like a wood chipper and you need something tougher and more predictable.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>13</readingTime></item></channel></rss>