<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Random Orbital Sanding on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/categories/random-orbital-sanding/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/categories/random-orbital-sanding/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Difference Between Da And Random Orbital Sanding</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/difference-between-da-and-random-orbital-sanding-random-orbital-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/difference-between-da-and-random-orbital-sanding-random-orbital-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 13:35:28 +0000</pubDate><category>Random Orbital Sanding</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-100</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-240</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-400</category><category>dust control</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><description>An engineer’s guide to the difference between DA and random orbital sanding, with test-based advice on speed, finish, abrasives, and setup.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="da-vs-random-orbital-sanding-an-engineers-guide"&gt;DA vs random orbital sanding: an engineer’s guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning in the shop, the kettle clicks off as the garage door rolls up and a slab of maple waits on the sawhorses. The winter light is unforgiving; it shows every swirl that last year’s “good enough” sanding left behind. In one hand: a well-balanced 5-inch palm sander; in the other: a heavier, gear-driven unit that can bulldoze epoxy ridges like a planer. The decision—random orbital sanding or the so-called DA—doesn’t feel philosophical. It’s practical. Do I want a fast, aggressive cut to level those glue lines, or a controlled, low-risk finish for the final passes? If you’ve ever chased phantom swirls under a bright lamp or watched edges burn through because you leaned a degree too far, you know the stakes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item><item><title>Prevent Swirl Marks With Random Orbital Sanders</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/prevent-swirl-marks-with-random-orbital-sanders-random-orbital-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/prevent-swirl-marks-with-random-orbital-sanders-random-orbital-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 02:33:16 +0000</pubDate><category>Random Orbital Sanding</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-800</category><category>dust control</category><category>grit progression</category><category>dry sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><category>orbital sander</category><description>Learn expert workflows to eliminate swirl marks with random orbital sanding—covering surface prep, abrasives, dust control, and inspection.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="prevent-swirl-marks-with-random-orbital-sanding"&gt;Prevent Swirl Marks with Random Orbital Sanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, low sun at the window, the first coat of finish flashes across the panel you’ve been nursing all week. The figure in the oak wakes up, but so do faint halos you didn’t see under shop lights. Swirl marks. You tilt the board, squint, and realize you were moments from locking those defects under a film for good. It’s a gut-punch that most woodworkers and finish carpenters eventually feel. The culprit is rarely the tool itself; it’s the stack of process decisions that lead to one outcome or the other. The relief is that processes are controllable, and with random orbital sanding done deliberately, swirls are optional.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>13</readingTime></item></channel></rss>