<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Metal Polishing &amp; Rust Repair on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/categories/metal-polishing--rust-repair/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 15:09:38 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/categories/metal-polishing--rust-repair/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Scratch Pattern Control For Metal Panels Before Primer</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/11/scratch-pattern-control-for-metal-panels-before-primer-metal-surface-sanding/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/11/scratch-pattern-control-for-metal-panels-before-primer-metal-surface-sanding/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 15:09:37 +0000</pubDate><category>Metal Polishing &amp; Rust Repair</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-120</category><category>grit-150</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-220</category><category>grit-240</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-600</category><category>grit-800</category><description>Learn expert scratch pattern control for metal panels before primer with step-by-step sanding, tool choices, and troubleshooting from a pro workshop</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="metal-surface-sanding-scratch-control-before-primer"&gt;Metal Surface Sanding: Scratch Control Before Primer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evening a panel is finally quiet is when the real work begins. You kill the grinder, and suddenly it’s just you, a breath of solvent in the air, and sheet metal that shows everything—every ding mapped by light, every shallow wave you swore wasn’t there in the morning. I’ve been there with a door skin laid across sawhorses, work lamp low and unforgiving, palm testing the temperature of steel that still remembers the sander. This moment decides whether primer becomes a friend that hides your sins or a megaphone that announces every missed step.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><media:content url="https://blog.equalle.com/images/brand/21.webp" medium="image"/><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>Identify Surface Rust Versus Scale And Perforation</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/identify-surface-rust-versus-scale-and-perforation-rust-repair/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/05/identify-surface-rust-versus-scale-and-perforation-rust-repair/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 04:10:19 +0000</pubDate><category>Metal Polishing &amp; Rust Repair</category><category>grit-80</category><category>grit-180</category><category>grit-320</category><category>grit-400</category><category>grit-1500</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>rust removal</category><description>Engineer’s guide to identify surface rust, scale, and perforation, with testing methods, abrasives, and rust repair decisions for lasting results.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="rust-repair-spotting-surface-scale-and-perforation"&gt;Rust Repair: Spotting Surface, Scale, and Perforation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning light caught the fender of my old wagon just right, the way it sometimes does when you’re not quite awake and not quite rushing. A faint blister under the paint telegraphed something I’ve learned to notice: the subtle topography of oxidation. It’s the kind of moment most of us meet with a sigh and a glance away. I paused instead. As a product engineer who’s spent years testing abrasives, primers, and coatings, I’ve learned that the difference between a quick cosmetic tune-up and a structural failure starts with how we look at rust—and how early we decide to act on it. Whether you wrench on weekends or you’re planning a professional rust repair, the first step is classification. Is it only surface rust that can be abraded clean? Is it scale that has undermined the steel layers? Or is it perforation where oxygen and time have already won a hole through the sheet?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>12</readingTime></item><item><title>Grit Progression For Aluminum Before Buffing</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/02/grit-progression-for-aluminum-before-buffing-metal-polishing/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/02/grit-progression-for-aluminum-before-buffing-metal-polishing/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 23:37:34 +0000</pubDate><category>Metal Polishing &amp; Rust Repair</category><category>metal polishing</category><category>grit progression</category><category>wet sanding</category><category>clear coat</category><category>sanding block</category><description>Learn grit progression for aluminum and master metal polishing. Achieve a flawless finish with our step-by-step guide and expert tips.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="mastering-metal-polishing-grit-progression-for-aluminum"&gt;Mastering Metal Polishing: Grit Progression for Aluminum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine standing in your workshop, the soft hum of machinery around you, the air filled with the scent of fresh metal shavings. It&amp;rsquo;s a place of creation, where raw materials are transformed into shining, polished works of art. You&amp;rsquo;re holding a piece of aluminum, rough to the touch, yet full of potential. With the right techniques, this unassuming piece can become a mirror-like masterpiece. The secret lies in grit progression—a meticulous, step-by-step process that transforms the mundane into the magnificent.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>6</readingTime></item></channel></rss>