<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Specialty Abrasives on eQualle Blog</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/categories/specialty-abrasives/</link><description>Recent posts on eQualle Blog</description><generator>Hugo 0.150.1</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://blog.equalle.com/categories/specialty-abrasives/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Film Backed Sheets For Uniform Scratch</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/film-backed-sheets-for-uniform-scratch-microfinishing-film/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/07/film-backed-sheets-for-uniform-scratch-microfinishing-film/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 15:23:44 +0000</pubDate><category>Specialty Abrasives</category><category>grit-2000</category><category>clear coat</category><description>Learn how film-backed microfinishing film sheets deliver uniform scratch patterns with step-by-step techniques, grit selection, and pro tips for flawless</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="microfinishing-film-uniform-scratch-every-time"&gt;Microfinishing Film: Uniform Scratch Every Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s late, the shop lights are a soft hum, and you’re chasing a finish that doesn’t lie—flat, even, and honest under any light. I know that moment well: when a part looks good to the naked eye, but under a raking beam the scratch pattern flares in swirls and hot spots. That’s where film backed sheets earn their keep. With microfinishing film, you don’t rely on luck; you rely on controlled, repeatable abrasion that leaves a uniform scratch from corner to corner. It’s the difference between “good enough” and “go ahead, mic it—twice.”&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>10</readingTime></item><item><title>Structured Abrasives For Predictable Cut</title><link>https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/structured-abrasives-for-predictable-cut-microfinishing-film/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.equalle.com/posts/2025/11/03/structured-abrasives-for-predictable-cut-microfinishing-film/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 20:03:50 +0000</pubDate><category>Specialty Abrasives</category><category>grit-800</category><description>Engineer-tested guide to structured abrasives and microfinishing film for predictable cut, selection, process control, and repeatable surface finish.</description><summary>&lt;h2 id="structured-abrasives-and-microfinishing-film-guide"&gt;Structured Abrasives and Microfinishing Film Guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few evenings ago I watched a machinist finish a crank journal by feel alone. The shop lights were warm, the radio low, and the final passes looked almost ceremonial—long, even strokes of a film-backed abrasive over an oil-wet rotating shaft. He paused, wiped the journal with a clean rag, and held a portable surface meter to the steel. The digital readout settled: within spec on the first try. That level of control doesn’t happen by accident; it’s a marriage of technique, process discipline, and the right abrasive architecture. In my experience, when you want a predictable cut and repeatable finish, structured abrasives and microfinishing film give you that control in a way conventional coated papers rarely can.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><readingTime>11</readingTime></item></channel></rss>